<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <!-- Note: these descriptions were generated by ChatGPT -->

    <string name="class_ceratopsian_description">
       Ceratopsians were herbivorous dinosaurs from the Late Jurassic to the Late Cretaceous, most famous for their large, bony frills and facial horns. These dinosaurs, like Triceratops and Styracosaurus, had parrot-like beaks for cutting through tough vegetation. Many species displayed elaborate frills and horns, likely used for defense, display, or species recognition. Ceratopsians were quadrupedal, with powerful neck muscles to support their heavy skulls, and they thrived in North America and Asia.
    </string>

    <string name="class_stegosaurid_description">
       Stegosaurids were herbivorous, quadrupedal dinosaurs best known for their double row of large, plate-like structures along their backs and spikes on their tails (thagomizer). Living during the Jurassic period, Stegosaurids like Stegosaurus had small heads, short forelimbs, and long hind limbs, giving them a distinctive posture. The function of the plates is debated, but they may have been used for thermoregulation, display, or defense.
    </string>

    <string name="class_ichthyosaur_description">
       Ichthyosaurs were marine reptiles from the Mesozoic era, thriving from the Triassic to the Cretaceous. They were highly adapted for life in the ocean, with streamlined, fish-like bodies, long snouts, and large, paddle-like fins. Ichthyosaurs, like Ichthyosaurus and Ophthalmosaurus, were swift swimmers, feeding primarily on fish and squid. Their large eyes suggest they had excellent vision, possibly aiding in deep-sea hunting.
    </string>

    <string name="class_abelisaurid_description">
        Abelisaurids were a group of theropod dinosaurs primarily known from the Cretaceous period, found in regions like South America, Africa, and India. These carnivorous dinosaurs were characterized by their short, deep skulls, robust hind limbs, and notably tiny, almost vestigial forelimbs. Unlike their larger relatives, such as Tyrannosaurs, Abelisaurids had shorter, stockier snouts and rough-textured skull bones, possibly for combat or display. Their most famous members include Carnotaurus and Majungasaurus. Abelisaurids were top predators in their ecosystems, adapted for swift, powerful bites and likely relied on ambush hunting tactics.
    </string>

    <string name="class_synapsid_description">
      Prehistoric synapsids, often called "mammal-like reptiles," were the dominant land vertebrates before dinosaurs, flourishing in the late Paleozoic era. They had a single temporal opening in the skull behind the eyes, a key trait that later evolved into the mammalian jaw structure. Synapsids varied greatly in size and form, with some being herbivores, while others, like the carnivorous Gorgonopsids, were apex predators. Many early synapsids, such as Edaphosaurus and Dimetrodon, laid the groundwork for mammalian evolution by developing differentiated teeth and other mammal-like characteristics.
    </string>

    <string name="class_sailed_synapsid_description">
       A subset of synapsids, including Dimetrodon and Edaphosaurus, which are notable for the large, spiny sails on their backs. These sails were formed by elongated vertebral spines connected by skin, possibly used for thermoregulation, display, or species recognition. Dimetrodon, a carnivorous predator, was one of the most famous sail-backed synapsids, known for its serrated teeth adapted for cutting meat. These sail-backed synapsids lived during the Permian period, long before dinosaurs, and played a key role in early vertebrate evolution.
    </string>

</resources>